Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. In this
walkthrough we are going to talk about WASM
and we're going to talk a little bit about
the hello world code. Now the the first
thing to say is that WASM now WAT is just
a syntax. It's the assembly language
for the machine language. And the first
thing to say is that unlike microprocessors
and assembly language and machine language,
it was never intended to be handwritten. And so
this is a little lot less convenient than even
assembly language. its goal is to be sort
of verifiable and safe. because JavaScript
and WASM are intended to run with code from many
different sources that doesn't necessarily want
to trust each other or have one piece of code
affect the other piece of code. And so it has
this concept of sandboxed execution so that no
matter what you do in your little sandbox, you
can take stuff in and give stuff back, but in your
sandbox you can't mess with anybody else's
sandbox. So there's a there's a goal of isolation.
So this language is designed for like isolation
first. It's designed to not allow you to write
code that could touch memory that doesn't belong
to you or anything like that. And so it's about
this isolation. The actual code model. First off,
you can see that it's very parenthesy based. And
the parentheses are like curly braces.
They're beginnings and ends. So what we're looking
at is hello world. It's not C. This is AI gave me
just some simple hello world was. Now in this
case we are using things like console.log from
JavaScript and passing into that console the
log message and the length of the log message.
And so this is code that is expecting to run in
a JavaScript environment and that console.log
will be available to it. And so there's an
import statement that basically says pull in
some code from JavaScript or give me access to
a log function from console.log function from
JavaScript itself. We're going to declare that we
need some memory. We're going to fill that memory
up starting at zero with the string hello world.
These are actually not zero zero terminated.
this is really a string that's 13 long. And
you'll see this 13 come in in a second. ,
and then we're going to make it so that the memory
is available to the JavaScript that's going to
call us. And then we have a main function that's
going to be called by the JavaScript. And ,
we're going to , call our log function and pass
the string and the length of the string. And then
we're going to return 42. Even main functions
like in C return values. And then we're going
to export the function main. And then there's
JavaScript that's going to call this function
main. So let's go ahead and compile and run
this. In this browser, there is a full WAT to
WASM compiler and then WASM to machine code and then
JavaScript to execute the resulting machine code.
And here is the actual WASM. So the so WAT is just
the is the assembly language. But the
ultimate thing is this is just a few bytes.
looks like about 6 * 16 about 100 bytes of
character and these are these are like
machine code but it is interpreted so this is
like a bite code in Java but it's
also intended that that it can be just in time
compiled into the real machine code after
validating the safety of it okay and so we
go from the watt to the WASM and then we execute
this WASM in Java JavaScript and JavaScript has a
WASM execution environment for it and then the
output comes back to JavaScript and away we go
and so so that is the hello world simple hello
world not a C hello world I'll show you that in
a bit but a WASM and JavaScript hello world that
does its printing using console.log log. Cheers.